Guide to the Ida Treat Bergeret Papers, 1889-1978
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
- Series XI. Published Articles by Bergeret
  - Nuages sur le Pacifique, parts 1-3, Vu, nos. 385-387, undated (Folder 2.170)
  - Nuages sur le Pacifique, parts 4-6, Vu, nos. 388-390, undated (Folder 2.171)
  - Nuages sur le Pacifique, parts 7-8, Vu, nos. 391-392, undated (Folder 2.172)
  - Nuages sur le Pacifique, parts 9-10, Vu, no. 393-394, undated (Folder 2.173)
  - Paris in the Morning, The Nation, p. 175-, 1946 Jan 17 (Folder 2.174)
  - Paris Looks at Everyman’s House, The Nation, p. 175-, 1946 Aug 17 (Folder 2.175)
  - The Pigeon Loft, The New Yorker, p. 95-, 1958 Mar 15 (Folder 2.176)
  - Prospecting for Buried Worlds, The Nation, v. 123, no. 3203, p. 528 -529, 1926 Nov 24 (Folder 2.177)
  - Reveillon in Paris, The Nation, p. 71-72, 1946 Jan 19 (Folder 3.1)
  - Sailing Forbidden Coasts, National Geographic, v. 60, no. 3, p. 356-372, 1931 Sep (Folder 3.2)
  - Sailing Forbidden Coasts, National Geographic, v. 60, no. 3, p. 373-386, 1931 Sep (Folder 3.3)
  - Sailor’s Wife, The New Yorker, p. 301, 1957 Jan 26 (Folder 3.4)
  - So Tall a Lady, The New Yorker, p. 26-, 1960 Jul 2 (Folder 3.5)
  - Sorcery in the Pyrenees, Travel (fragment), undated (Folder 3.6)
  - The Third Monsieur, The New Yorker, p. 20-, 1954 Jul 31 (Folder 3.7)
  - To Celebes, The New Yorker, p. 152-, 1963 Oct 26 (Folder 3.8)
  - Watch Dogs of the High Seas, Travel, v. 80, no. 3, p. 4-, 1943 Jan (Folder 3.9)
  - When Reindeer Roamed the Pyrenees, parts I and II, Scientific American, 1929 Dec, 1930 Jan (Folder 3.10)
  - Young China Plans for the Future, Travel, p. 16-, [1936 Oct 1?] (Folder 3.11)
- Series XII. Translations and Reviews by Bergeret
  - "The House of Stupidity," by Alberto Savinio. Translated from Italian, undated; (TS) (Folder 3.12)
  - "Homer Barchetta," by Alberto Savinio. Translated from Italian, undated; (TS) (Folder 3.13)
  - "My Mother Does Not Understand Me," by Alberto Savinio. Translated from Italian, undated; (TS) (Folder 3.14)
  - Re: Alberto Savinio: Notes, undated (Folder 3.15)
  - Review: Behind the Urals, by John Scott, Political Science Quarterly, v. 57, no. 4, p. 601-604, undated (Folder 3.16)
- Series XIII. Manuscripts by Others
  - Dorothy Treat: Report on the Geology of Boulder and Latimer Counties., undated (Folders 3.17-3.29)
  - Dorothy Treat: Story of Owls, undated (Folder 3.30)
  - [Simone Begouen?]: Letter from North Africa [Morocco?], undated (Folder 3.31)
  - [Simone Begouen?]: Letter from North Africa [Morocco?], undated (Folder 3.32)
  - Unidentified Manuscript, undated (Folder 3.33)
- Series XIV. Articles by Others
  - Aven, Mark: "On the Bridge", undated (Folder 3.34)
  - Begouen, Max: "Dessins Abstraits et Figurations en ‘Perspective Tordue’", undated (Folder 3.35)
  - Fournier, Willy: "Sauvetage", undated (Folder 3.36)
  - Igolen, Georges: "Roses of the Dadès", undated (Folder 3.37)
  - [Savinio, Maria?]: "Quadri ad Ago", undated (Folder 3.38)
  - Tongue, Margaret: "Icharus and Dedalus, Walter on Monday,", undated (Folder 3.39)
  - Walker, Joseph A.: Top Flight, undated (Folder 3.40)
  - White, E.B.: Farmer White’s Brown Eggs, undated (Folder 3.41)
- Series XV. Poetry by Others
  - Tongue, Margaret: Poetry, undated (Folder 3.42)
  - Tongue, Margaret: Poetry, undated (Folder 3.43)
  - Miscellaneous Poetry, Ballads, etc., undated (Folder 3.44)
- Series XVI. Articles By and About Teilhard de Chardin
  - L’Afrique et les Origines Humaines, undated (Folder 3.45)
  - Breuil: Le Père Teilhard et Son "Phenomene Humain", undated (Folder 3.46)
  - Breuil, Abbe H. "Soixante ans de découvertes... ", undated (Folder 3.47)
  - L’Energie Humaine, p. 1 – 17, undated (Folder 3.48)
  - L’Energie Humaine, p. 18 – 40, undated (Folder 3.49)
  - L’Energie Humain, p. 41 – 59, undated (Folder 3.50)
  - L’Energie Humain, p. 60 – 69, undated (Folder 3.51)
  - L’Humanité se muet-elle biologiquement sure elle-même?, undated (Folder 3.52)
  - Une interpretation biologique plausible de l’Histoire Humain: la Formation de la "Noosphère.", undated (Folder 3.53)
  - Introduction a la Vie Chretienne, undated (Folder 3.54)
  - La Paléontologie et l’Apparition de l’Homme, undated (Folder 3.55)
  - Le Pere Teilhard de Chardin, undated (Folder 3.56)
  - Pour y Voir Clair. Réflexions sur Deux Formes Inverses d’Esprit, undated (Folder 3.57)
  - Quelques Réflexions sur la Conversation du Monde, undated (Folder 3.58)
  - Le rebondissement humain de l’évolution et ses conséquences, undated (Folder 3.59)
  - Sauvons l’Humanité, undated (Folder 3.60)
  - Science et Religion: Sont-elles incompatables?, undated (Folder 3.61)
  - La Structure Phylétique du Groupe Humain, undated (Folder 3.62)
  - La Structure Phylétique du Groupe Humain, undated (Folder 3.63)
  - Les Unités Humaines Naturelles.. ., undated (Folder 3.64)
  - Unidentified Typescript [Evolution], undated (Folder 3.65)
- Series XVII. Clippings
  - Primitive Hearths in the Pyrenees, undated (Folder 3.66)
  - Reviews: The Anchored Heart, undated (Folder 4.14)
  - Reviews: In France it was Spring, undated (Folder 4.15)
  - Reviews: Pearls, Arms, and Hashish, undated (Folder 3.67)
  - re: André Bergeret, undated (Folder 4.16)
  - re: Paul Vaillant-Couturier, undated (Folder 4.17)
  - re: Paul Vaillant-Couturier, undated (Folder 4.18)
  - re: Teilhard de Chardin, undated (Folder 3.68)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, undated (Folder 4.19)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, undated (Folder 4.20)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, undated (Folder 4.21)
- Series XVIII. Financial Papers
  - Banque de Bretagne, undated (Folder 3.69)
  - Banque de Bretagne, undated (Folder 3.70)
  - Contracts, undated (Folder 4.22)
  - Contracts, undated (Folder 4.23)
  - Contracts: The New Yorker, undated (Folder 4.24)
  - Royalty Statements, undated (Folder 3.71)
- Series XIX. World War II
  - Cadran, undated (Folder 3.72)
  - Clippings, undated (Folder 3.73)
  - Documents and Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated (Folder 3.74)
  - Invasion Diary, 1944 Jun 6 - Sep 2 (Folder 3.75)
  - Tricolore, vol. IV, no. 6, undated (Folder 3.76)
  - Tricolore, vol. IV, no. 8, undated (Folder 3.77)
  - Tricolore, vol. IV, no. 9, undated (Folder 3.78)
  - Tricolore, vol. V, no. 4, undated (Folder 3.79)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Folder 3.80)
- Series XX. Printed Material
  - Archives Internationales Claude Bernard re: Philippe Decourt, undated (Folder 3.81)
  - Archives Internationales Claude Bernard re: Philippe Decourt, undated (Folder 3.82)
  - First American tour of Mei Lan-Fang, undated (Folder 3.83)
  - Hommage à Leon Moussinac, undated (Folder 3.84)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 3.85)
- Series XXI. Diaries
  - Diary: Ida Treat Bergeret, 1926 (Folder 3.86)
  - Diary: Ida Treat Bergeret, 1943 Jan-Feb (Folder 3.87)
  - Diary: Ida Treat Bergeret, London, 1944 (Folder 3.88)
  - Diary: Ida Treat Bergeret, 1950 Sep - Jun (Folder 3.89)
  - Diary: Ida Treat Bergeret, 1953 Jun - 1957 Nov (Folder 3.90)
  - Diary: Ida Treat Bergeret, 1953-1960 (Folder 3.91)
  - Diary: Ida Treat Bergeret, 1954-1958 (Folder 3.92)
  - Diary: Ida Treat Bergeret, circa 1977 Jun - Aug (Folder 3.93)
  - Diary (?): notes, Ida Treat Bergeret "Mes lettres à Paul", undated (Folder 3.94)
  - Diary: Dorothy Treat, 1961 Feb - Mar (Folder 3.95)
- Series XXII. Biographical: Ida Treat Bergeret
  - Autobiographical, undated (Folder 3.96)
  - Clippings, undated (Folder 3.97)
  - Obituary, undated (Folder 3.98)
  - Résumé, undated (Folder 3.99)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 3.100)
  - Trips, undated (Folder 3.101)
  - Trips, undated (Folder 3.102)
  - Trips: notes, undated (Folder 3.103)
- Series XXIII. Drawings
  - Drawing by B. Palencio for Ida Treat, undated (Folder 5.1)
  - Facsimile of drawing: "La Mère de Paul sur son... ", undated (Folder 5.2)
  - Drawings: "Primitive Hearths in the Pyrenees", undated (Folder 5.3)
  - Drawings: "Primitive Hearths in the Pyrenees", undated; [see also box 24, folder 468] (Folder 5.4)
- Series XXIV. Photographs and Scrapbooks
  - André Bergeret, undated (Folder 5.5)
  - Ida Treat Bergeret, undated (Folder 5.6)
  - Ida Treat Bergeret, undated (Folder 5.7)
  - Paul Vaillant-Couturier, undated (Folder 5.8)
  - Paul Vaillant-Couturier, undated (Folder 5.9)
  - Pére Teilhard de Chardin, undated (Folder 5.10)
  - Treat Family, undated (Folder 5.11)
  - Treat Family, undated (Folder 5.12)
  - Treat Family, undated (Folder 5.13)
  - Treat Family, undated (Folder 5.14)
  - Treat Family, undated (Folder 5.15)
  - Bouillon, undated (Folder 5.16)
  - Bouillon, undated (Folder 5.17)
  - China, undated (Folder 5.18)
  - Djibouti, undated (Folder 5.19)
  - [Early Chapters of a Biography], undated (Folder 5.20)
  - "Primitive Hearths in the Pyrenees", undated (Folder 5.21)
  - World War II [unidentified individuals], undated (Folder 5.22)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 5.23)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 5.24)
  - Five (5) Tintypes, undated (Folder 5.25)
  - Two (2) watercolors by Paul Vaillant-Couturier, undated (Folder 6.1)
  - One (1) photograph album, undated (Box 6)
  - Two (2) scrapbooks, undated (Box 6)